The Search for Signs of Intelligent Life in the Universe is a
comedy, tv movie film directed by John Bailey.
The filmed version of the one-woman stage show written by Jane Wagner and starring Lily
Tomlin, which won the Drama Desk Award for Unique Theatrical Experience.
The film stays true to the original stage performance.
For her efforts on film and stage, Tomlin received a Tony Award, and Funniest
Actress in a Motion Picture in the American Comedy Awards.
Trudy the Bag Lady / Agnus Angst / Kate / Brandy / Tina / Chrissy / Lud /
Marie / Vince / Edie / Lynn / Marge, played by Lily Tomlin.
The Search for Signs of Intelligent Life in the Universe (1985)
is a one-woman stage show written by Jane Wagner.
The original Broadway production starred Lily Tomlin, won the Drama Desk Award for
Unique Theatrical Experience, and was turned into a film in 1991.
The show, Tomlin's second Broadway billing as a solo performer, follows Tomlin as she performs
various characters or personae, all while wearing simple black pants and a white blouse.
The show appears disparate at first, but becomes unified under the sensibility
of the opening "bag lady" persona as the performance progresses.
The show is often praised or considered controversial for its feminist material, most
notably the compressed history of the feminist movement offered in Act 2.
For her stage performance, Tomlin won a Tony, Drama
Desk, and Outer Critics' Circle awards.
A film version was directed by John Bailey and edited by Sally
Menke, and stays true to the original stage performance.
The film earned the Golden Space Needle Award at the
Seattle International Film Festival.
For her efforts on the film, Tomlin received a Funniest Actress in a Motion
Picture American Comedy Awards, amongst other notable accolades.
A restored version of the film, compiled from different prints, was shown at the 2024 RescueFest
at the Laemmle Monica Film Center in Santa Monica, California in December 2024.
The tone is lighthearted.